Fanuel N. Alem

Oakland, CA 94609

Phone: 510-452-7283 | Email: fanuelnalem@outlook.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/fanuel-alem-12991b32/ | GitHub: https://github.com/fanuelalem |

Portfolio: https://fanuel-portfolio.herokuapp.com/

Summary

A Full Stack Web Developer leveraging a background in client management and I.T support to build intuitive and pleasant user experiences on the web with a life-long dedication to learning. Effective at combining creativity, technical skills, and problem solving to develop user-friendly Web Applications. Known as a hard worker among staff for strong wit and attention to detail no matter the complexity of the project!

Technical Skills

- Problem solving, Teamwork, Creativity, Communication, Adaptability and Autonomy.
- HTML, CSS, jQuery, React, Node.js, SQL, NOSQL, Es6 Javascript, WordPress
- User Directory, Note Taker, Day Planner, Weather Dashboard, Code Quiz, Employee Management System

Projects

Admin App | https://github.com/fanuelalem/AdminApp | https://carnatakehomeproject.herokuapp.com/ A language learning educational app built with React and Semantic UI front-end framework, NodeJs and express back-end, JWT and local authentication, and MongoDB. Users can practice and review their progress and teachers can assign exercises.

- Created a backend and built queries using MongoDB, NodeJs, and PassportJs.
- Utilized React and other Front-end frameworks to build styled web components.
- Configure and administer Heroku and git version control to deliver, monitor, and host applications on the cloud.
- MERN Stack (MongoDB, Express, React, Node.js), Redux, Bcrypt, Passport, JSON web tokens)

<u>The Jedi Code</u> | https://github.com/fanuelalem/Project-02 | https://thejedicode.herokuapp.com A Star Wars themed Full Stack application that calculates a user's answers in a personality quiz to determine which character they are most similar to.

- Collaborated with a team of 4, and participated in the decision-making process, coding, testing, and debugging.
- Created API routes and SQL queries using NodeJs and back-end frameworks(Express).
- Completed the application in less than 2 weeks collaborating remotely using Zoom and Slack.
- NodeJs,SQL, React, Git, Bootstrap, Heroku

StockTracker | https://github.com/fanuelalem/Project-3 | https://stocktracker1ofor1o.herokuapp.com/ A MERN stack authenticated application where users can create an account, search any stock in the market, view daily top gainers and losers, and save stocks onto a watchlist.

- Collaborated with a team of 4, helping with the decision-making process as well as coding, testing, and debugging to make MVP.
- Created API routes and MongoDB schemas with NodeJs and backend frameworks(Express).
- Built the application interface using React and the backend using NodeJs and Express along with MongoDB

- Configure and administer Heroku and git version control to deliver, monitor, and host applications on the cloud.
- Met a 2 week deadline while working remotely using Zoom and Slack.
- MERN Stack (MongoDB, Express, React, Node.js), Redux, Bcrypt, Passport, JSON web tokens)

Experience

Lead Software Engineer, San Francisco, Ca

Carna May 2021 - Present

- Develop the front and back ends (full stack) of a web-based application in JavaScript.
- Design, implement, and maintain database schemas.
- Keep all technical documentation updated and create new documentation as needed.
- Participate in the Agile software development life cycle (stand ups, code reviews, group testing, etc.)

Lead Front-End Web Developer, Remote

Abe Legal November 2020 - May 2021

Worked as a part of a cross-functional team of 4 to help identify business needs, assist in planning and developing projects, and creating and executing test plans that will help to deliver a quality product. Was involved in testing and modifying the platform's user interface to let lawyers scale themselves 100x more effectively.

- Heavily utilized 4-5 web technologies and tools including HTML,CSS,JavaScript, Bootstrap, Paypal API Integration, and Canva.
- Incorporated Search Engine Optimization techniques into the platforms to boost rankings of platforms on all search engines and app stores and driving traffic up 200%.
- Document and review product requirements as needed and launch the Abe Legal platform.
- Manage product development budget and third party vendors.

Account Manager, San Francisco, CA

TechSoup Nov 2018 - December 2019

At Techsoup, I Investigated and resolved a wide variety of issues and requests to include probing for additional information from customers and setting expectations.

- Worked as part of a 9-12 team of account-management specialists dealing with 1.2 million active customers.
- Managed client inquiries of google products including G suits, google ads, youtube, google earth and maps.
- Handled company data using excel spreadsheets to do fraud audits and reviewed 50-100 companies per day.
- utilized management skills, data analysis, communication, and improved in communication and paying attention to details.

Junior Web Developer, Oakland, CA

Renaissance Entrepreneurship Center March 2015 - February 2016

- Build, extend, and deploy website landing pages using HTML,CSS, and JavaScript.
- Modify website architecture components as needed using front-end tools.
- Develop high quality and test-able code that can be utilized across multiple browsers and devices.
- Work with UX teams to ensure usability and quality.
- Track assigned projects on your own.
- Perform client-facing duties as needed such as leading technology discussions, product training, etc.
- Work cross-organizationally with multiple teams and individuals.

Education

Bootcamp Certificate

University of California, Berkeley

- Programming using Object Oriented Programming (OOPs concept) and software development life cycle (SDLC), architecting scalable platforms, database design and agile methodologies. Writing and Using different APIs.
- Creating interactive and user friendly UIs. Designing and developing full-stack applications across multiple platforms using modern industry- adopted languages and frameworks.
- Leveraging cloud services like GitHub, Heroku, Google App Engine.
- Architected and developed NodeJs and Express for the backend development and front-end application using React, Redux, and ES6/7 and MongoDb/SQL for database.
- Used React JS in components like JSX, creating React components, Virtual DOM, React Props, Lifecycle methods, working with React States and Events.
- Analyzing, developing and implementing web-based applications.

Bachelor's Degree

San Francisco State University, San Francisco, CA

Acquired a degree in business administration where I have been exposed to web development in my Computer Science courses. Participated in a group project where we created a website using Wordpress